Guide to the August Claessens Papers TAM.021
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
August Claessens Papers
1906-1963
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Claessens, August, 1885-1954
TAM.021
2.5 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes.
August Claessens was a leading educational and political figure in the Socialist Party. In the fall of 1917, Claessens was elected to the New York State Assembly, as a representative of one of Manhattan's Lower East Side assembly districts, and was one of five socialist assemblymen who the Assembly refused to seat after their 1919 reelections. In 1922, Claessens was allowed to take office after being re-elected for the third time. In the mid-1930s Claessens withdrew from the Socialist Party and became the executive secretary and, later, the national chairman of the Social Democratic Federation. Claessens held the position of national chairman until his death in 1954, and also ran unsuccessfully for a number of local and state offices. Claessens taught a variety of subjects at the Rand School of Social Science from the mid-1920s until his death in 1954, including public speaking, psychology, race relations, labor-management relations, socialist theory, politics, anthropology, and sex and society. Claessens also served as an instructor in several evening schools sponsored by various New York City labor unions. The collection contains manuscripts, lecture notes, correspondence, photographs, clippings, and printed ephemera.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Rand School Archives, 1962. Earlier provenance information is unknown. The accession numbers 1962.006 and 1962.016 are associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
August Claessens (1885-1954) was one of the most influential leaders in the educational and political development of the Socialist Party. Shortly after becoming a socialist in 1909, Claessens helped organize support for the Socialist Party within several New York City labor unions. In the fall of 1917, Claessens was elected to the New York State Assembly. As a representative of one of the Lower Manhattan assembly districts, Claessens drafted and worked for legislation pertaining to child labor, the penal code's procedures for obtaining an admission of quilt, the abolishment of the Volstead Act, the abolishment of the death penalty, and the regulation of police powers in suppressing strikes.
On April 1, 1920, Claessens was one of five socialist assemblymen who were expelled from the State Assembly on the grounds that membership in the Socialist Party constituted disloyalty to the United States. Although legally represented in the fight to retain his office by Charles Evans Hughes, a future United States Supreme Court Chief Justice, Claessens was denied his seat throughout the turbulent period of the Red Scare. In September 1920, Claessens was re-elected to the State Assembly in a special election, but again the anti-socialist forces, led by Assembly Speaker Thaddeus C. Sweet, refused to permit Claessens to take office. Finally, in 1922, Claessens was allowed to take office after being re-elected to the State Assembly for the third time.
In the mid-1930s Claessens withdrew from the Socialist Party and became the executive secretary and, later, the national chairman of the Social Democratic Federation. Claessens held the position of national chairman until his death in 1954. Besides his involvement with the Social Democratic Federation, Claessens also ran unsuccessfully for a number of local and state offices.
Claessens was one of the most active faculty members at the Rand School of Social Science. From the mid-1920s until his death in 1954, Claessens taught courses in such subject areas as public speaking, parliamentary procedure, psychology and social psychology, race relations, labor-management relations, socialist theory, contemporary politics, anthropology, and sex and society. Claessens also served as an instructor in several evening schools sponsored by various New York City labor unions. At these schools, Claessens primarily taught courses in public speaking and labor-management relations.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents August Claessens's involvement with the Socialist Party and his work as a lecturer and New York State assemblyman, primarily from the 1920s to the 1940s. The majority of the collection consists of manuscripts and notes of Claessens's lectures, pamphlets, books, addresses, and statements, with emphasis on themes of labor, socialism, and socialist humor. Other genres of materials include correspondence, photographs, and biographical materials.
The researcher should note that an error was made in the targeting for this collection. On each frame the word "Series" appears adjacent to the frame number. This term should actually be interpreted as "Collection."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series. The correspondence is arranged chronologically, the manuscript and lecture notes are arranged alphabetically, and Series III and IV are arranged topically.
I. Correspondence
II. Manuscript and Lecture Notes
III. Photographs and Printed Materials
IV. Biographical Clippings and Published Writings
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Several collections at the Tamiment Library (including the records of the Rand School of Social Science) have been microfilmed as one collection, the Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956 (Film R-7124). There is also a published guide to the microfilm collection, Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: A Guide to the Microfilm Edition, edited by Thomas C. Pardo (REF HX81.T36).
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version, with the exception of Box 5; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reel 56.
Pamphlets.; Manuscripts for publication.; Lectures.; New York (State) -- Politics and government.; Photographs.; Speeches.; Socialism -- United States.; Articles.; Rand School of Social Science; Branstetter, Otto; Steinke, Leo; Hillquit, Morris, 1869-1933; Friedman, Esther; Social Democratic Federation of America; Socialist Party (U.S.); Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971; Russell, Charles Edward, 1860-1941; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967
- Series I. Correspondence, 1911-1963, 465222
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I consists of letters and telegrams containing information on socialist publications and activities, Claessens's 50th birthday and 25th year as a Socialist Party member, and other personal matters. Several letters from Claessens emphasize the importance of humor in public speaking. Some of the prominent correspondents in this series include Morris Hillquit, Otto Branstetter, Leo Steinke, Esther Friedman, Carl Sandburg, Charles Edward Russell, and Adolf A. Berle, Jr.
  - Correspondence, 1911; 37077 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV:A
  - Correspondence, 1912; 37076 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1913; 37075 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918; 37074 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1920; 37073 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1921; 37072 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1927-1928; 37071 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1934; 37070 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1935; 37069 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1937; 37068 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938; 37067 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1941; 37066 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1944; 37065 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1945; 37064 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1946; 37063 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1948; 37062 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1950; 37061 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1951; 37060 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1952; 37059 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1953; 37058 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1954; 37057 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1955; 37056 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1963; 37055 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hilda Claessens Correspondence, 1915, undated; 37053 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: B
- Series II. Manuscript and Lecture Notes, 1906-1954, 36970
  This series (XIV:C), consisting of 78 subject files, includes manuscripts and notes of lectures, pamphlets, books, addresses, and statements. Each subject file within this series has been given a frame number and has been cited according to the title of the file in the complete reel list. In some instances, the titles of items within the subject file are cited in the complete reel list. Of special interest in this series are Claessens's writings on socialist humor, particularly the rough draft of his book, Didn't We Have Fun? (XIV:C:13); a series of articles entitled, "Revolutionary Fun" (XIV:C:56); and a collection of anecdotes entitled, "We Struggled With a Smile" (XIV:C:73). This series also contains writings on human nature, prejudice, prohibition, contemporary politics, labor, socialism, heredity and environment, sex and society, and religion. A collection of seven poems (XIV:C:45), written by Claessens, are also included in this series.
  - ABC of Parliamentary Law, undated; 37051 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: C
  - Anthropology and the Growth of Society Contains 5 brief lectures: - The Origin of Man and the Races of Mankind - Primitive Man and His World - The Savage and His Culture - The Barbarian and His World - Civilization, undated; 37050 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - [Article on the 1932 campaign], 1933; 37049 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Can a Goy and a Yiddina Stay Happily Married?, undated; 37048 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Changing Human Nature, undated; 37047 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Chase for the Almighty Dollar, The End of the Chase, undated; 37046 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Collective Bargaining, undated; 37045 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Collectivism and Individual Liberty, Feb 1951; 37044 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Communism, undated; 37043 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The Cultural Elements, undated; 37042 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Democracy vs. Dictatorship, Nov 1939, June 1941; 37041 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Democratic Way of Life, undated; 37040 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated; 37039 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated; 37038 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated; 37037 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Didn't We Have Fun?, undated; 37036 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Disagreeable and Dirty Work, undated; 37035 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Einstein Theory, undated; 37034 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Elementary and Advanced Socialism, contains: Our Economic Chaos (3 copies) Lessons from the World War (2 copies) What Socialism Is (3 copies) The Distribution of Wealth (2 copies) The Love of Money The Odium of Menial Labor Instinct of Workmenship (2 copies) Incentive and Ambition (3 copies) Socialism and Ambition, 1930-1935, undated; 37033 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Elements of Social Progress, 1934; 37032 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ethics and Economics, undated; 37031 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Evolution of Morality, 1933; 37030 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Florida Violence, undated; 37029 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Genius, undated; 37028 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Germany and Reparations, undated; 37027 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Graft and Corruption (4 copies), Mar 1932; 37026 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Guaranteed Annual Wage, undated; 37025 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Haiti, undated; 37024 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Heredity and Environment, contains: Our Natural Heritage Our Natural Environment Nature and Nurture Problems of Physical Heritage Our Social Environment Our Social Heritage Problems of Social Heritage, 1931-1933, undated; 37023 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - If Lincoln Were Hoover, undated; 37022 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Immigration, undated; 37021 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Industrial Democracy, undated; 37020 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Is A United States of Europe Possible?, 1950; 37019 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Is Socialism Inevitable?, undated; 37018 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Is the Status of the Masses Improving?, Is the Condition of the Masses Growing Better or Worse?, undated, 1934; 37017 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Jew and the World Crisis, undated; 37016 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Justice Without A Blindfold, undated; 37015 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Labor Movement, undated; 37014 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Lectures on Behavior, contains: The Instinctive Basis of Behavior Acquired Behavior - The Environmental Factors (2 copies) Social and Collective Behavior, 1940, undated; 37013 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - A Liberal Interlude (3 copies), undated; 37012 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Measures to Halt a Depression, 1954; 37011 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Modern Science, Man, Religion and God, undated; 37010 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Must We Change Human Nature?, undated; 37009 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Nature of Work and the Nature of Man, undated; 37008 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - NRA (4 copies), Oct 1933; 37007 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Outlines and Highlights of the Social Sciences Biology Human Geography: The Cultural Backwardness of the South Psychology Social Psychology-Prejudices and Stereotypes Anthropology, undated; 37006 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Patriotism, undated; 37005 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Poems, contains: Remembrance (2 copies) On a Spring Greeting Card to Jennie (2 copies) Friendship Winter Enthusiasm The Months (2 copies) A Bit of Philosophy-Before Election, 1906-1920, undated; 37004 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Prejudices-A Story in Human Behavior, 1932-1943; 37003 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Prohibition, undated; 37002 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Promise of Socialism, undated; 37001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Prosperity and Hard Times, Dec 1923; 37000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Racketeers and Big Business, undated; 36999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Red Riots, undated; 36998 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Relation of Work to Ignorance and Education, undated; 36997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Religion and Soviet Russia, undated; 36996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Resolution on African Independence (2 copies), undated; 36995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Resolution on Anti-Semitism, undated; 36994 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Revolutionary Fun contains: They Were All One to Him (2 copies) That Was the Purpose of the Meeting Obliging He Never Spoke on That Corner Again (2 copies) Got a Permit (3 copies) May Day Article Close Shave (2 copies) Kindly Suggestion (2 copies) Some Diet! It Can Happen Only in Harlem (2 copies) A Four Hour Day Hamlet Outdone Suggestively Ancient misses A Question in Physics Not an Encyclopedia Mathematics One on History One on the Professor One on the Teacher Biology as Franklin No Doubt Knew Three Humorous Bits: Phrenology an Englishman's Idea of American Humor Change of Nationality Mythology Materialism Versus Spiritualism, undated; 36993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Second Industrial Revolution, undated; 36992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sex and Society contains: Women and Modern Industry Prostitution Marriage and Economics The Home-Present and Future The Home and Social Changes Marital Incompatibility Mental Differences of Men and Women (2 copies) Sex Prejudices, 1930-1935, undated; 36991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Social Attitudes Toward War and Peace (2 copies), 1936; 36990 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Social Psychology (4 copies), 1935-1938; 36989 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Socialism and Human Nature, undated; 36988 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Socialism and Religion, undated; 36987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Socialism and Social Problems, undated; 36986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Socialism of George Bernard Shaw, undated; 36985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Socialism in the Assembly, undated; 36984 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Stock Market, undated; 36983 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - These United States, 1935; 36982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Unavoidable Hazard in Some Kinds of Work, undated; 36981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Understanding the U.S.A., undated; 36980 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Understanding the Worker, undated; 36979 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - United Front, undated; 36978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Wages and Prices, undated; 36977 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - We Struggled with a Smile contains: An Innocent Deception (3 copies) On the Plains of Colorado (3 copies) Good Heavens! (3 copies) A British Prime Minister Meets His American Comrades (3 copies) I Work with a Notorious Racketeer Some Funny Moments in the Labor Movement The Germans in Our Midst The Benefits of Materialism (2 copies), undated; 36976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - What Organized Labor Has Gained, undated; 36975 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - What Organized Labor Wants, undated; 36974 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - The Will to Live, undated; 36973 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Why They Threw Us Out of the Assembly, undated; 36972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Notes, undated; 36971 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Series III. Photographs and Printed Materials, 1909-1953, 36968
  Series III contains 26 photographs (XIV:D) that are arranged in chronological order and include portraits of August Claessens, group photographs, photographs of Claessens with other socialist figures, and photographs of Claessens teaching at the Rand School. Each photograph has been labeled with a number in the lower right-hand corner of the picture. These numbers correspond with the description of the photographs in the complete reel list. There are also approximately 20 photographs of Claessens and his family and friends which have not been microfilmed.
  The printed matter in this collection (XIV:E) is organized into the following seven subject files: (1) Claessens legislative bills, New York State Assembly; (2) election campaigns; (3) lecture announcements; (4) miscellaneous; (5) pamphlets; (6) socialist legislative bills, New York State Assembly; and (7) testimonials. Each subject file has been assigned a frame number, including each item in the pamphlets file.
  The legislative bills constitute the largest bulk of materials in the printed matter series. These bills are divided into two files: (1) 16 bills drafted by Claessens from 1918 to 1919 (XIV:E:1); and (2) 74 bills drafted by the five socialist assemblymen during the period, January-April 1918 (XIV:E:6). The bills drafted by the five socialist assemblymen include legislation on the regulation of municipal street railway fares, municipal ownership of public utilities, repeal of the state police department, abolishment of the death penalty, regulation of child labor, reorganization of the City College of New York, expansion of workmen's compensation, free university education, and the establishment of municipal day nurseries.
  This series also includes five pamphlets which were written by Claessens (XIV:E:5). A bibliographical citation for each pamphlet in this file can be found in the complete reel list.
  - Photographs 1- 9. Portraits of August Claessens nd Photograph 10. Four of the five Assemblymen expelled by the New York State Assembly during the Red Scare. L-R: Charles Solomon, Louis Waldman, Samuel Orr, August Claessens ca. 1920 Photograph 11. Socialist agitators who toured the United States and spoke at Socialist meetings in many states, 1921. L-R, front: Isidore Goldstein and Norman Goldstein. L-R, rear: Sylvia Claessens, Hilda Claessens, August Claessens. ca. 1921 Photograph 12. August Claessens in his office at the headquarters of the Social Democratic Federation, New York City. 1935. Photograph 13. August Claessens, center in the second row, at an outing of the Young People's Socialist League. 1935. Photograph 14. August Claessens conducting a class in economics and public speaking at Local 62 of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union. 31 March 1936. Photograph 15. August Claessens speaking at an "Open Air" meeting in New York City. nd. Photograph 16. August Claessens speaking at an "Open Air" meeting and encouraging workers to read socialist publications. nd. Photograph 17. Part of a crowd attending a Socialist Party rally in New York City. nd. Photograph 18. August Claessens, center in the second row, with other Socialists and union members. nd. Photographs 19-21. August Claessens giving a lecture. nd. Photograph 22. August Claessens, far left, and one of his numerous Rand School classes nd. Photograph 23. August Claessens teaching a class in public speaking at the Rand School, January 1932. Photograph 24. August Claessens addressing a group of trade union representatives, nd. Photograph 25. August Claessens giving an address, nd. Photograph 26. August Claessens, center of the photograph, attending a dinner, nd., ca.1920-1940; 36969 (Box A001, Folder 1)
    (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: D
  - Claessens, General, undated; 465224 (Box A001, Folder 2)
    General
    Items not microfilmed.
  - Claessens Legislative Bills, New York State Assembly, 1918-1919; 36967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    (Socialist Collections Reel 56) Frame XIV: E
  - Election Campaigns, 1940, undated; 36966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lecture Announcements, 1914-1953, undated; 36965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1909-1922, undated; 36964 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Pamphlets, Contains: 1. Claessens, August. The Blue Eagle Is Dead? So What! New York: New York Socialist Party, nd. l6pp. 2. Claessens, August. Is Socialism Inevitable? An Explanation of the Forces of Social Progress. Chicago: Socialist Party of the United States, 1922. 40pp. 3. Claessens, August. Roparska Trojica. Chicago: Jugoslovanska Delavska Tiskovna Druzoba, 1924. 63pp. 4. Claessens, August. The Trinity of Plunder. A Cheerful Slam at Rent, Interest, and Profit. New York: New York Call Printing Co., 1922. 32pp. 5. Claessens, August. Zasady Socjalizmu. Detroit: Wychodzi kazrdego.tygodnia, nd. 18pp., 1922-1924, undated; 36963 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Legislative Bills, New York State Assembly, Jan 1918-Apr 1918; 36962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Testimonials, Feb 13, 1928-Apr 22, 1950; 36961 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Duplicates of Microfilmed Items (I), undated; 36960 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Item not microfilmed
  - Duplicates of Microfilmed Items (II), undated; 36959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Claessens Pamphlets A-E (I), 1930s-1940s; 36958 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Claessens Pamphlets A-E (II), 1930s-1940s; 36957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series IV: Biographical Clippings and Published Writings, 290880
  This series consists of biographical clippings and published writings which were not microfilmed.
  - Claessens Book Reviews, undated; 36956 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Claessens Newspapers Articles, Debates, etc., undated; 36955 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Claessens Articles, undated; 36954 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - BF: Biographical File, undated; 36953 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1912; 36952 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1915; 36951 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1919; 36950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1933; 36949 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1934; 36948 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1937; 36947 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1940; 36946 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1942; 36945 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1944; 36944 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - BF: Biographical File, 1947; 36943 (Box 5, Folder 15)